RICHARD F. TAYLOR, Ph.D.

Dr. Taylor has proven leadership in designing, implementing and managing complex multidisciplinary product development and commercialization programs for diagnostic, pharmaceutical, food, fine chemical, nutritional supplement, and medical device companies. His experience is grounded in technology with functional expertise in team building, R&D planning and implementation, scale-up and production, technology assessment, regulatory compliance, marketing, and strategic alliances and partnering. Dr.Taylor also has experience as an expert witness in biotechnology, pharmaceuticals, diagnostics, and nutritional/dietary supplements.

EXPERIENCE

1997- TC ASSOCIATES INC., West Boxford, MA (www.tcaonline.com)

President and Senior Consultant

TCA is a Management and Technical Consulting firm serving diagnostic, pharmaceutical, and food companies worldwide. TCA aids clients in planning and implementing R&D programs, and guides clients in identifying technologies, markets, partners and acquisitions to complement and extend product lines.

2005-2015 UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS, Lowell, MA

Adjunct Professor, Department of Clinical Laboratory Sciences

Dr. Taylor taught a graduate course he wrote in Molecular Diagnostics and Advanced Clinical Diagnostic technologies, product development, and markets.

2004-2006 **TECAN GROUP (**www.tecan.com)

Director, LabCD Programs (2005-2006)

Senior Scientist, Advanced Product Development (2004-2005)

Hands-on R&D of new ADMET, genomic and immunoassays for drug discovery and diagnostics based on Tecan's centrifugal microfluidics technology. Evaluation and formation of partnerships to develop new products using LabCD IP and technology.

2001-2005 UNIVERSITY OF NEW HAMPSHIRE, Durham, NH

Adjunct Professor, Departments of Chemistry and Animal & Health Sciences Dr. Taylor taught two, graduate-level courses he wrote on the development, production, regulation, and commercialization of new pharmaceutical, biotechnology, and diagnostic/genomic products: Molecular Diagnostics and Applied Biotechnology

2001-2004 **CENTERBRIDGE, INC.,** Lincoln, MA (www.centerbridge.com)

Vice President, Diagnostic Technology

Centerbridge provided a new approach to home health care, linking home diagnostic tests to wireless technology for monitoring and reporting the health status of patients

1977-1997 **ARTHUR D. LITTLE, Inc.,** Cambridge, MA (now Tiax LLC, www.tiax.biz) Founded in 1886, ADL provided management and R&D consulting services worldwide

Manager and Director, Applied Biotechnology

Founded the Applied Biotechnology Laboratory in 1986, to provide consulting and laboratory services to pharmaceutical, food, and diagnostic companies, including:

- Development and commercialization of immunoassay kits and instruments, nucleic acid probes, chemical and biological sensors, microarrays, downstream processing
- Technology-driven market reviews, regulatory reviews and strategic positioning studies for new biotechnology products; DSP and production studies

Phone: 978-352-7047 eMail: TCAdtaylor@cs.com Spectrum Ex. 1040 IPR Petition - US 8,084,443

page 2 of 2

• Invented, patented and directed the development of new products including, drug delivery products, immunoassays, biosensors, microarrays, food products

Manager and Director, Separations and Analytical Sciences

Assumed management and reorganized the ADL separations' development laboratory in 1990, providing consulting and laboratory services in analytical and bioanalytical chemistry for food, pharmaceutical and biotechnology products including:

- Development of new analysis and QAQC methods and instrumentation
- Development of GLP/GMP methods and protocols for use in preclinical and clinical trials of new pharmaceuticals and biopharmaceuticals
- Technical development and management audits of R&D programs and manufacturing streams for pharmaceutical and biotechnology products.

Principal, Biological Development Laboratories

One of three founders in 1991, of a new business unit to provide consulting and laboratory services for moving new drugs through the FDA regulatory process.

- Directed the development and implementation of new GLP/GMP analysis methods for pharmaceuticals and biopharmaceuticals
- Built a business with \$3 million in sales in 2 years' time
- BDL was spun-off in 1993, and purchased by Genzyme in 1995

Senior Consultant, Technical and Business Services

Worldwide name recognition in multiple technical areas. Author of over 40 technical and business reports for **Decision Resources**, **Inc.** focused on the commercialization of new products including:

- Worldwide Immunoassay Markets, Technologies and Applications
- Separation Technologies: Markets and Applications
- Biosensors: Technology, Applications and Markets
- The Outlook for DNA/RNA Probes in U.S. Clinical Diagnostics Markets
- Has established, over 40 years, a worldwide network of clients and contacts in North America, Eastern and Western Europe, Japan, China and the Middle East.

EDUCATION

- Ph.D., Biochemistry, University of New Hampshire, Durham
- B.S., Chemistry, the St. Lawrence University
- NDEA Fellowship, University of New Hampshire.
- NATO Postdoctoral Fellowship, U. College of Wales, UK
- British SRC Fellowship, U. College of Wales
- U.S. NRC Fellowship, Naval Medical Research Institute, Bethesda

PROFESSIONAL HONORS, ACTIVITIES, AND AFFILIATIONS

- Member, Beta, Beta, Beta, National Biological Honor Society; Sigma Xi; the American Chemical Society; the American Society for Microbiology; the American Society of Pharmacognosy; the Undersea Medical Society; the New York Academy of Sciences; the International Cell Research Organization, AAAS, AACC
- Special Technical Advisor to the United Nations in Argentina (neurochemistry), and the People's Republic of China (natural colorants/vitamins and biotechnology).
- Author of over 125 scientific articles, books, and patents in the areas of biochemistry, toxicology, neurophysiology, in vitro diagnostics, pharmaceuticals, analytical chemistry, microbial physiology, immunochemistry, protein immobilization, sensors and arrays.
- Author of over 50 market reports on biotechnology, pharma and diagnostic markets.
- Editorial Review Board, In Vitro Diagnostics Technology, Skin Pharmacology Physiology